<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Projects on Jeff Sawalha</title>
    <link>https://jsawalha.github.io/jeff_portfolio/post/</link>
    <description>Recent content in Projects on Jeff Sawalha</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <language>en-us</language>
    <lastBuildDate>Thu, 02 Mar 2017 12:00:00 -0500</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="https://jsawalha.github.io/jeff_portfolio/post/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Project # 2: Predicting pediatric anxiety from the temporal pole using neural responses to emotional faces</title>
      <link>https://jsawalha.github.io/jeff_portfolio/post/project-2/</link>
      <pubDate>Sat, 21 Aug 2021 11:00:59 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jsawalha.github.io/jeff_portfolio/post/project-2/</guid>
      <description>The second project involved functional neuroimaging for children suffering from anxiety disorders. Specifically, this was a dataset of 45 children (aged 5-9), who were shown images of fearful, angry and neutral faces, while they were under an fMRI scanner. Our goal was to classify anxious and non-anxious children based strictly on their neuroimaging data. Using advanced computational algorithms, we were successfully able to classify children with various anxiety disorders. More interestingly, our model identified a relatively unknown area of the brain that best distinguished these individuals.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Project # 1: Individualized identification of first-episode bipolar disorder using machine learning and cognitive tests</title>
      <link>https://jsawalha.github.io/jeff_portfolio/post/project-1/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 18 Dec 2020 10:58:08 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jsawalha.github.io/jeff_portfolio/post/project-1/</guid>
      <description>This was a publication examining neurocognitive data in patients with bipolar I disorder (BD). We wanted to examine the correlation between certain neurocognitive deficits and the number of manic / psychotic episodes in first-episode and chronic-BD participants (FE-BD &amp;amp; CHR-BD). The overall objective of this study was to identify individuals who are in the beginning stages of bipolar disorder by learning the more nuanced cognitive deficits that CHR-BD participant’s display in their neurocognitive tests.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Project # 3: X-ray classification of pneumonia</title>
      <link>https://jsawalha.github.io/jeff_portfolio/post/project-3/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 05 Mar 2019 11:13:32 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jsawalha.github.io/jeff_portfolio/post/project-3/</guid>
      <description>Here, I obtained a dataset from a popular website called Kaggle. Here, there are over 5000 images of chest x-rays, and half are suffering from pneumonia. The performance task was simple: Train a classifier that can detect which x-rays represent pneumonia patients.
Here is a list of skills I deployed for this project:
 Used PyTorch to train a convolutional neural network (CNN) Standardized x-ray images, which included: resizing, centering, randomized horizontal skips, randomized rotations, randomized gray scaling, and tensor transformations Achieved a balanced accuracy of 82%   Above is an array of x-ray images   </description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Project # 4: Detecting presence of PTSD using sentiment analysis from text data</title>
      <link>https://jsawalha.github.io/jeff_portfolio/post/project-4/</link>
      <pubDate>Wed, 12 Apr 2017 11:14:48 -0400</pubDate>
      
      <guid>https://jsawalha.github.io/jeff_portfolio/post/project-4/</guid>
      <description>Sentiment analysis refers to the use of natural language processing to extract emotional content from text information. In our paper, we train a machine learning model on textual data, to identify individuals with PTSD using sentiment analysis from semi-structured interviews. Our sample size included 188 individuals without PTSD, and 87 with PTSD. The interview was conducted by an artificial character (Ellie) over a video-conference call. Our model was able to achieve a balanced accuracy of 80.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
